Hey בוקר טוב. boker tov.
29th day of the Omer. דף כג Daf Chaf Gimmel in מעילה
Meilah but second פרק perek of קינים. Kinnim. And we had learned
yesterday basic principles about a what was called in the first פרק
perek חובה, Chova, actually in this פרק perek is called a קן
סתומה, Kan Stuma, an undifferentiated nest. In the first פרק perek it's
called a חובה, Chova, an obligatory nest, where half of
where one is a one is a חטאת Chatas and one is
an עולה. Ola. And if you have a large one, multiple obligations
all bundled up, then half of them are חטאות Chataot and half
of them are עולות. Olot. And we talked about the scenario of
thank you so much of two of those types of groups getting
mixed up where you could only bring half of them as a
חטאת Chatas and עולה Ola because as soon as you do more
we won't go over the scenario again but as soon as you
do more you might be bringing more than the right you might
be bringing from one group more than 50% חטאות
Chataot or more than 50% עולות. Olot. Okay, so
and we also talked about a case where one specific thing, an
עולה, Ola, went into a group and then you can only bring
the עולות Olot and only there the amount that it started with.
So that was too quick, whatever, I gave yesterday. Let's take a
look at now this פרק perek where the second משנה mishna is
going to be the big challenge, but after that it'll be a
lot easier. So we'll start with the first משנה. mishna. קן סתומה
שפרח ממנה גוזל לאויר או שפרח לבין המתות או שמת אחד מהן.
Kan Stuma sheparach mimena gozal la-avir o
sheparach levein hametot o shemet echad mehen.
So pretty easy scenario. You have an undifferentiated group, you know, two
birds, one will wind up being a חטאת, Chatas, one will be
an עולה, Ola, and one of them flew away. It either just
flew out somewhere in the world, or it flew amongst other birds
that have to die for reasons like we talked about last פרק.
perek. So this is also and obviously can't be determined which, so
it's gone as well. או, o, or died. So what do you
do? So the answer is easy. יקח זוג לשני. Yikach zug lesheni.
You just pair it up. It's sort of like the, you know,
the two goats of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. One of them dies,
you pair it up. You know, some of the מפרשים meforshim say
that maybe I would have thought that if they've already been differentiated,
one the חטאת, Chatas, one the עולה, Ola, then it's obvious, my
עולה Ola dies, I buy another עולה, Ola, my חטאת Chatas dies,
I buy another חטאת. Chatas. But maybe if they're not differentiated, maybe
somehow their like fates are intertwined. So what it's telling you that's
not true. If one of them dies, you just buy a second
one, fine.
By the way, what's not spelled out here is an interesting question
is, you know, if you buy that second one later, but it's
implicit that then you can go back to being this undifferentiated group.
You know, you can buy another one in its undifferentiated state and
it just, you know, and it goes back to the as it
was before. Fine, that's an easy case. Now we go to the
next case, which is going to be what is going to drive
the following משנה. mishna. פרח לבין הקרבות. Parach levein hachrevot.
Now
you have something that goes, you have let's say let's take a
case of two groups, each one of four. Each group has, you
know, two two pairs in it, two קינים kanim in it. Each
group of four, right? So in each group there's going to be
two חטאות, chataot, two עולות, olot, but undifferentiated. Okay. Now one animal
one bird for one group flew into לבין הקרבות, levein hachrevot, into
another group that would have been offered. So now you have three
and five. You got the math, four and four, now you have
three and five. What's the הלכה? halacha? How much can you bring
from each group? So פסול, pasul, it is invalid, ופוסל אחד כנגדו,
uposel echad kenegdo,
and it and it invalidates one opposite it. שהגוזל הפורח shehagozel haporeach
because a bird that flies, פסול, pasul, is invalid, ופוסל אחד כנגדו,
uposel echad kenegdo,
and invalidates one opposite it. Now what does this mean?
Well same thing we were saying yesterday?
Yes. So what we're saying I mean, same principle, but just different
scenario. So let's spell it out. So let's say you've got here,
let's I could draw it on the board but let's see, give
me some of those things, I'll use them as my little example,
these
pomegranates. Alright, here we go. So you've got three here, we'll use
these as maybe other things. Okay, you've got three and five, right?
One flew you had four and four, but one flew. And now
you've got three and five. What can you bring? So let's start
over here.
So why not just bring all three, what the heck? Because if
you bring all three, right, you let's say let's say call it
two חטאות chataot and an עולה. ola. Okay, no problem, I mean
from this, right, you can define what it's going to be, it
was undifferentiated and then you're getting you had four and four, now
you have three and five. What are you going to bring from
this? So go ahead and bring two חטאות chataot and an עולה.
ola. Why not, it's all undifferentiated, you can pick, right? Problem is
like this, if you do that, then then if you use this
as two חטאות chataot and an עולה, ola, what does it turn
out that you've turned this into? An עולה. ola.
An עולה, ola, right? Okay. No, if this is two חטאות chataot
and an עולה ola and this came from this group, then by
definition this is an עולה, ola, right? If this now you've made
this into an עולה, ola, okay, and now it's in this group,
now you've limited this whole group of only bringing two עולות. olot.
Remember the הלכה, halacha, if an עולה ola flies into... group you
can only bring the עולות olos and only the base from it
starts with. So that is going to too much restrict what you
can bring from the second group. You don't want to determine, do
something here that's going to create this as a fixed identity.
The second group belongs to someone else, right?
It might, or it might not.
And why is that group, why does it care if that's a
set group? Yeah. Why does it matter if some unidentified bird flies
into it? They are set.
You mean you mean you should act regardless of how it affects
somebody else?
Why should it affect them?
No no no, this is this is a group of קרבנות korbanos
that somebody else is going to bring. It might even be a
group that I'm going to bring.
You mean you
mean no no no wait a second wait a second these are
my קרבנות korbanos these are Michael's קרבנות. korbanos. This bird flies here.
If I act sort of in disregard of Michael and bring all
these three I'm going to have it's going to create too much
of a negative impact on Michael because by bringing one of my
birds is still here. If I bring all these...
But why is it here if it's your bird?
You don't know which one it is.
You don't know which one it is. If he brings if I
do this and by my act I automatically make this into an
עולה olah then Michael Michael might bring a bird call it a
חטאת. chatas.
He doesn't know which one.
Yeah yeah that's the whole point if he knew which one I
could just retrieve it. He doesn't know which one. Okay? So I
don't want to fix this identity as an עולה olah because then
that overly restricts Michael. He doesn't know which is which. All right?
Is that clear now? Yes?
It's hard to believe how that could happen if you're bringing birds
you've got them in some kind of a pen right?
I mean I know I don't know if this actually flies
and they've got to be in a stray in some way.
I know I don't know if this actually really happened. It was
an opportunity for them to do some interesting math in הלכה halacha
okay? All right. So that's where I do not want to bring
all three. That's going to create this as a fixed identity and
overly restrict Michael. I'm only going to bring two. I'm going to
bring a חטאת chatas and an עולה. olah. Okay? Now therefore this
identity is not fixed because it's only going to fix when when
it's clear what it is. But it isn't clear what it is.
If you see I could make this a חטאת chatas this will
be an עולה. olah. I can make this an עולה olah this
will be a חטאת. chatas. So this identity remains in flux. Got
it? Now what's Michael going to bring?
But once it once you do fix it I mean some point...
No we're going to go through without fixing it you'll see. So
Michael's going to bring we're not going to fix both right you'll
see. Because I left one over let's say I brought two what's
Michael going to bring?
He can bring all of them.
No. Why? I can't bring something that's not
no I don't mean all of them I mean he can bring
two and two right?
He can bring two and two right right.
He can bring his.
Right. Well but he doesn't know which is his. He could bring
two and two. Why could he bring two and two? Because he
brings well let's just start with why can't he bring all? No
okay that's what let's just explain. Why can't he bring all? Bring
all of them right? It doesn't matter because you know the pair
of this is here this one isn't being brought right? So why
not bring all? So the reason he wouldn't bring all well what's
he going to bring? He has five. So he's going to bring
what? Three חטאות chataos and let's say two עולות. olos. Let's say.
He can't bring a חטאת chatas of something you can't...
Yeah but maybe it's not a חטאת chatas fine whatever he brings
three עולות olos and two חטאות. chataos. You know why it's not
going to work? Let's say he decides that he's going to bring
these three as עולות olos these two as חטאות. chataos. That worked
because these two are עולות olos these two are חטאות chataos and
this which was anyway mine and that's an עולה olah that'll be
good. But he doesn't know what he's bringing. And when he says
he's bringing three חטאות chataos and two עולות olos he might bring
this as his three I mean as his three עולות. olos. Three
עולות olos all three from his original four right? But he was
only able to bring two עולות olos from his original four. So
therefore because he can by bringing more than his base two and
two he might take have taken them all from his original four
and therefore taken too many of one type. So therefore he's only
allowed to bring two of each and one he has to leave
over. Maybe it's mine maybe it's not mine it doesn't matter. This
one is in flux. This one's identity can be determined because I
left one over. But the only thing is you can't take three
of one type because it might be all from the original group.
That's why I can't bring any from your group. What? I thought
like the problem is it's your group and therefore I can't...
No we're all allowing it to happen so that the maximum can
be brought. And then the כהן kohen is going to bring it
according you know for whomever it goes for. You're not bringing it
for your it'll be brought for whomever it deserves to be brought
for. That one of the חטאות chataos
has to be brought לשמה. lishmah.
Okay so if you have a סתם כוונה stam kavanah it works
also so long as you're not bringing it לשם leshem for some
other owner. Okay? So the basic הלכה halacha therefore is what happened
when one flew over? We're going to bring two from here and
four from here. Yes? Did we all see that? Why? We leave
one over in order to let this be in flux and we
only and we don't bring all here because you might get the
proportions wrong you know where you selected from. So that's the הלכה
halacha of פסול. pasul. It is invalid in the sense that of
the five here one can't be brought. We don't know which one
but we're not going to bring one. And it's פוסל אחד כנגדו.
posel echad kenegdo. It invalidates one opposite it. Okay? So one from
the one if from the group it left you can't bring one
the group it left has three now you can only bring two
and from the group it... went into, you can't bring one, you
can only bring four. So that is the principle that the flying
bird you can't bring one from the group it left; it has
three but you can bring two, and I can't bring one from
the group it flew into, we can't bring five you can only
bring four. The same thing if it was two to four right?
What?
If it was different numbers, different sized groups.
Yes, if two
flew then you can't bring four.
Yes, right. And that's going to be the next משנה Mishnah *Mishna*.
Okay. All right. That was easy enough, that was the easy part.
Let's keep us going.
And these two are left to die? Yeah.
כיצד keitzad, *Keitzad*, so now the next משנה Mishnah. *Mishna*, how is
this true? שתי נשים לזו שתי קינים shtei kinim ולזו שתי קינים
kinim, *Shtei nashim
lezo shtei kinnim ulezo shtei kinnim*. Two women, each one has, here's
the scenario I just gave you, two pairs, each one has a
group of four. פרח מזו לזו *Parach mizo lezo*, a bird flew
from one to the other. פוסל אחד בהליכתה *Posel echad bahalichatah*. So
it invalidates one in its first flight. Now because it flew into
Michael's group there and it invalidated one as we said, I mean,
one from what it left behind, one from where it went into.
Now of course since that wasn't interesting enough, now it flies back.
Now if it flew back then no problem then we're back to
where we started from. But no, a bird flew in the back
and you don't know which bird. וחזר *Vechazar*, and where was I?
וחזר *Vechazar*, a bird went back. פוסל אחד בחזירתה *Posel echad bachaziratah*.
It invalidates another one in its return. Now what does that mean?
Well now as this yes this is going to be I'll figure
out an easy way to simplify this. Now if one bird flew
back right? You have five and three and one bird flew back
and you had four and four. So now the simplest scenario where
everything would be good is if you have is if you have
all of the original. Right. But the more complicated scenario is that
you have one bird off from each one.
So imagine basically
like you have like this, this is your first set, right?
And
this is your second set, right? You have one off bird in
each one. Now what can you do?
Oh you're already saying one flew into the other.
So one flew in each direction. In each right and then in
the best case scenario it's the same one and it's all good.
In the worst case scenario you have an exchange of birds, right?
I don't understand why you have three A's and one B. Because
it has it's already moved back and forth already.
If only one bird flew this way and only one bird flew
that way.
Right, so then what's your A and what's your B?
A is the original. This is the group that originally was all
A and this is the group that originally was all B. This
started out as four A's, this started out as four B's. Clear?
Yes, fine. Okay. So now what would you now what can you
do? Well if you're lucky, right, and you'll bring this is a
חטאת Chatat *Chatat* and an עולה Olah, *Olah*, this is a חטאת
Chatat, *Chatat* and an עולה Olah, *Olah* right from the original group.
Okay. And then you have like a lot of latitude here right
because what can you do? You can bring since these are pairs
here you could bring I don't know this is a חטאת Chatat,
*Chatat* this is an עולה Olah *Olah* and you're still okay because
it hasn't been fixed because this is left over. Anything that's left
over allows that to be flexible and unfixed. So if you knew
you were starting with this, you'd be great. You could bring more
than four. Is that clear? Because like you do those and then
all of these are still unfixed and therefore you can at least
bring these two because if these remain unbrought then those are flexible
to define what their status is.
Which means you can bring everything what you're saying?
What? You said you could bring everything. As soon as you brought
this, as soon as you brought this it would determine this what
this was. Right. And if this was a חטאת chatas *Chatat* this
would be an עולה olah *Olah* and you wouldn't know and you
might bring it the wrong way. Okay. So if you were lucky
and you brought this first you would actually be able to bring
six. But you might not necessarily be lucky. What might happen? What
you might wind up doing here, I'll use a different pen,
is you might wind up bringing this as a חטאת Chatat, *Chatat*
and an עולה olah. *Olah* and this is a חטאת Chatat *Chatat*
and an עולה Olah, *Olah*. That's in your worst case scenario, right?
So חטאת Chatat *Chatat*, עולה Olah *Olah*, חטאת Chatat, *Chatat*, עולה Olah
*Olah*. Now in your actual worst worst case scenario you've actually done
what I've just said. Not only have you brought these as חטאת
Chatat, *Chatat* and עולה Olah, *Olah* but you brought the A's of
the same type and the B's of the same type. Okay. Now
that you've brought two חטאת Chatat, *Chatats* from A, can you bring
another A? No. Because as soon as you bring another A you
might bring it as a חטאת Chatat. *Chatat* and it can only
now be an עולה Olah *Olah*, right? Is that clear? So don't
say oh bring the A as an עולה Olah *Olah*. You don't
know! It might be the reverse. It might be you've brought both
A's as עולה Olah. *Olah*. You can't, right? So in this type
of scenario you cannot bring another A because you might have already
fixed the A and you don't know how you fixed them. And
you can't bring another B because you've already fixed the B's and
so the other B's are חטאת Chatat *Chatats*, and therefore you might
be picking a B but you don't know how you fixed the
B. So because in this is that pretty clear? Sort of?
I don't know why I'm lost at the beginning example here because
if they're all undetermined at the beginning then why and one went
into each. What's the reason why you can't just make them all?
Oh, because the fact they're indeterminate but they are of different groups,
at least we sort of said yesterday. You can't combine different groups
into one big homogeneous sort of group. Once it's defined as a
different group, its identity is determined by the original members of that
group. Is that clear? Meaning, yes, you can't make this a new
group of eight. Or maybe this... I mean a new group of
of eight. Because then you'd have a lot of flexibility. You have
to always treat it as two groups of four and be concerned
with where the original one came from. And therefore since this was
originally from the group of B's, once three B's are brought, its
identity is fixed. Okay, is that clear? Okay. So therefore in this
case, because you might wind up doing ABAB, and they might be
the A's are the same and the B's are the same, but
you don't know which one, you can't bring anything more because it
could now be that all the rest of the birds are determined,
right? Is that clear? So in this case, you only bring four.
Okay, so what's the הלכה? halacha So the הלכה halacha? here is
חזר ופרח. chazar uparach.
Same thing as the case as the scenario before.
Well, just showing you that it works, it's just carrying it out
to the next stage. Okay. So it's no, חזר ופרח, chazar uparach,
so where, what is the הלכה? halacha חזר ופרח chazar uparach פוסל
אחד בחזירתו. posel echad bachazirato. One invalidates in its return. So basically
the הלכה halacha? is like this. If you look at it sort
of more generally of this group A and B, right? So one
bird went into A and went out of A. And in each
case, one bird went in and out. What do we learn? That
when a bird comes in, it invalidates two when it and when
a bird goes out, it invalidates... Remember the first scenario, when there's
five and three, one became פסול pasul from the one it left
and became פסול pasul in the one it went into. So here,
it went in and out, so when it went in, it invalidated
one and went out and invalidated one. So this is a minus
two. This also had in and out, so this is a minus
two. You can't use two from here, you can't use two from
here. So therefore you can only use two from each group. Okay?
Yeah? Every time a bird comes in or a bird goes out,
it's a rule, you lose one, you can't be מקריב makriv for
one. Yes, but the problem is, here's the problem as we're going
to see as the משנה Mishnah, continues. It's trying to make this
a general mathematical principle, but it doesn't... the log... it's not always
logically true that you lose one each time it goes in and
out. So far it's been working. Okay, we'll see in the next
משנה. Mishnah, But the משניות Mishnayos are working with the assumption that
this is the rule: you lose one when it goes in, one
when it goes out. So it's important to point out why how
you can see why that's true at least in this case. But
for the next case, it won't be so obvious. Okay? Now, that's
that case. Now it says like this:
פרח וחזר פרח וחזר. parach vechazar parach vechazar. Now let's say birds
fly back and forth and back and forth and back and forth
a dozen times. לא הפסיד כלום. lo hisid klum. You didn't lose
anything more. Why? שאפילו הן מעורבות אין פחות משניים. she'afillu hen me'uravot
ein pachot mishnayim. Even if they're mixed, they're never fewer than two,
or two pairs. Remember what we were teaching in the last פרק,
perek, that if you have two separate undifferentiated groups that get completely
mixed up, you can at least bring, if they're the same size,
you can always bring half. If they're different sizes, you can bring
the size of the smallest one. Okay, we discussed why that was
true yesterday. So here it's saying no matter how many times it
flies back and forth, it's not going to be worse than a
full mixing of the two groups. And we know that the principle
of a full mixing of the two groups is you get, if
they're same size, you bring half. So in this case you're already
bringing half, right? Each group is four, you're already just bringing two
out of each, you're already just bringing half of the half of
them. So it doesn't matter how many times back and forth. At
this stage anyway you're down to the minimum. The minimum you'll ever
be able to bring from these groups even in complete mixture is
going to be half their size and that you've already done. So
at this stage it won't matter. Of course if the group started
as ten, then it would matter. Every time back and forth would
keep on reducing it, how many you can bring till the absolute
minimum which would be the size of the smallest group, which is
what we learned yesterday. Okay, now we get to משנה ג'. Mishnah
Gimmel. Different size groups and multiple flyings. לזו אחת ולזו שתים ולזו
שלש ולזו ארבע ולזו חמש ולזו שש ולזו שבע. lezu achat ulezu
shtayim ulezu shalosh ulezu arba ulezu chamesh ulezu shesh ulezu sheva. You
have seven different women. Each one has a different number of, now
the one, two, three, four here are not number of birds like
the previous משנה, Mishna, they are a number of pairs, קינים, right?
שתי קינים in the previous משנה, Mishna, here too, number of pairs.
Now, פרח מן הראשונה לשנייה ולשלישית ולרביעית ולחמישית ולשישית ולשביעית וחזר. parach
min harishonah lashniyah velashlishit velarvi'it velachamishit velashishit velashvi'it vechazar.
So that case is like a whole loop now. Yeah. Sort of
passed the ball around and around.
That case is just... wait.
After we finish this, we're all going to say, "Why did we
learn this?"
Okay, anyway.
So, here you have one, two, three, each one of these represents
also number of pairs. Five, six, and seven. Okay, and a bird
flew
here, here... not obviously the same bird would make life easy. Okay,
and then first it flew... flew like... flew like this, and
then... Okay, what's the
הלכה?
Halacha So, let's take a look.
So it says, somebody's going to have to be watching these birds.
They were never marked. Yeah, exactly. Just to figure out what happened.
Right. Spooky. Exactly. I'm telling you, they were having fun, it was
an opportunity to do math להלכה. l'halacha. Okay, anyway, so it says
like this. Okay. וחזר פוסל אחד בהליכתו ואחד בחזירתו. V'chazar posel echad
bahalichato v'echad bachazirato.
So this is the principle we said that it invalidates one in
its going and one in its returning. Which means what? הראשונה והשנייה
אין להם כלום. Harishona v'hashniya ein lahem klum.
One and two groups, I'll read it and then I'll explain it.
Groups one and two can't bring any from groups one and two.
שלישית יש לה אחת. Shlishit yesh la achat.
The third one, which normally you could have brought three groups, now
only one. So each one is basically losing two groups. Okay? So
one and two started with one and two groups, so they get
down to zero. Three started with three groups, it gets down to
one. הרביעית יש לה שתיים. Harvi'it yesh la shtayim. Four brings two.
חמישית יש לה שלוש. Chamishit yesh la shalosh. Five brings three. שישית
יש לה ארבע. Shishit yesh la arba. Six brings four. Each one
loses two groups. השביעית Hashvi'it number seven יש לה שש yesh la
shesh brings six because it's an end point, so it only loses
one not two. What does this mean? First I'm going to explain
it based on the math of the previous משנה, Mishna the rule
of the previous משנה, Mishna. but then I'm going to point out
whether logically it makes sense. So the rule of the previous משנה
Mishna. was
every time a bird comes in or goes out it loses one.
Right? That was the rule of the previous משנה. Mishna. Okay, now
so let's understand. For number one, a bird went out and a
bird went in. Okay, so how many birds does it lose? Two.
Okay. For number two, a bird went in and a bird went
out, a bird went in and a bird went out. So it
loses four, right? And number three: in, out, in, out, loses four,
right? Everybody with me? Yeah. And number seven is an end point,
a bird went in and a bird went out, how many does
it lose? Only two birds, right? Now those are number of birds,
so number of pairs is half that. Okay. So this loses, so
this loses one pair. Okay. This loses, these all lose two pairs.
And all this loses one. So one and two starts with one
and two pairs, so they are down to zero. Right? All of
these lose two pairs. So one, two, three, is that clear? Yeah.
You have the pairs it's losing. Okay. Right? Are you with me?
Ignore if this is confusing. Okay? Losing two pairs, right? So it
starts with three, three minus two is one, right? Everything in the
middle loses two pairs. This loses one pair, it's six. That's the
משנה. Mishna, Based on the principle that every time a bird goes
in or out it loses a bird. So these things, here you
had it lose two birds, it loses one pair, two birds. All
of these have lost four birds, two pairs. So they all go
down to two. So these have zero, these have two here, that
has six. That's the משנה. mishna Now let's see if it really
makes sense. Okay? Because that's really the problem. Michael says oh it's
all obvious. Sure, it's obvious if you just assume the rule works.
But as the מפרשים Meforshim points out, is this clear as it
is? No, sort of?
It says every time, if you just believe the first משנה, mishna
that every time a bird goes in and out it loses two
birds, so it loses a pair. So all of these things have
had that happen twice, so all of these lose two pairs. Okay?
You can't bring two pairs. Okay. Now the problem is that if
you explain what the logic for it, the logic is, if you
remember, that you don't want to, you don't want to sort of
bring too many of one type. You don't want to fix, your
stuff might be mixed up with something else, and you don't want
to fix the thing that's mixed up because then it'll wind up
being brought in the wrong way. Right? That's the basic form. Okay,
so here's the deal. Number one lost a bird. This bird of
number one is flying somewhere here in the ether. Somewhere, it's somewhere
amongst those other birds. Okay?
It's left with its own little bird. I don't know if I'm...
it's left with its little bird. Okay. Now, you don't want to
bring that bird. Why don't you want to bring that bird? Because
if you bring the bird that it's left
with, that חטאת Chatat or עולה, Olah that'll make this fixed, and
then this is mixed up in all this stuff and might be
brought the wrong way. Is that clear? Meaning if you only started
with two, right? You're number one, two birds. One of them flew
away. If you were to bring the remaining bird, yes? Then you
would define this identity and then that gets you into trouble. You
need to leave this identity open
so you need to not bring... Right, because then every other person's
bird is a חטאת, Chatat right? Exactly. Then every other bird... Well,
yeah, I mean not exactly because if you bring this as a
חטאת, Chatat then everything else has to be brought as an עולה,
Olah, so you don't have to die but anyway... But if you
brought it as an עולה Olah and everything... Anyway, it would severely
limit. You don't want to fix this identity because it would severely
limit.
You don't even know that that bird is the same one that
keeps flying. Why do you have to keep track?
No,
but you do know you lost a bird, so your original bird
is somewhere here. You don't know where it is, maybe it's in
set two, who knows where it is? It's somewhere. And if you
bring this, well, it could
have actually come back to you.
It could, but you don't know that. It might be somewhere here.
And since you, so you can't bring this because then you wind
up fixing its identity. Okay, so that's point number one, you cannot
bring the bird that remains. Okay. Now, why can't you bring the
bird that returns? Because the bird that returns also, the whole point
is that it got mixed up. You don't know which is which.
So even though you have two birds here, one might be the
bird that remained, and then that would fix its identity. So that's
why you can't bring any of number one. Fine. Now let's talk
about number two. Number two lost, the easy point here is focus
on not the birds that came in, those are irrelevant, focus on
the birds that left. Okay, so number two lost two birds, right?
It
lost one bird in that direction and one bird in that direction.
So here's a little number two with wings, number two with wings,
I don't know,
anyway, and here's the number two with wings. Okay, so you have
left here two number twos. Now, you don't want to bring them,
right? Because if you bring them, you wind up fixing the identities
of those. Okay, and if you fix the identity of those, then
you're going to get into trouble in terms of the, you know,
because then it'll have these other implications. So therefore now, why don't
you bring one of them? Hold
on. Why don't you bring one
because,
I'm not exactly sure why you can't bring one. You can't bring
both, because then
you'd be fixing one, aren't you?
No, because you only, that there's two remaining, you're not fixing the
one. I have
to think back about
it, I have to think back about it some more. But anyway,
you certainly can't bring both of those. So therefore, that's what it
says, you certainly number two does not have a full pair that
can be brought. Maybe you could bring one, I have to think
about it, but it certainly doesn't have a full pair that can
be brought. Okay now, now
let's go on to number three. Number three, you've got, it lost
also two, right? So you have one three going this way and
one three flying that way. So how much do you have left?
Well,
you started with three pairs, so you have left two pairs, right?
Right, two pairs. So now here, you can bring one pair because
the rest, these things are not yet fixed, right? They're only going
to become fixed if you get into, now again, I'm looking at
the whole pair, so probably you could bring one pair. But if
you were to bring this whole next pair, right, then you actually
get fixed, okay? So you've got in three, now in three you
have, remember, birds flew in. You've got other birds here as well
that flew into three. Right, remember, you've got two birds, you actually
have three groups, but you can only bring one pair. Why can
you only bring one pair? Because as soon as you try to
bring another pair, you might be hitting this other pair and then
you've fixed the identity of the others.
Did each have two pairs to begin with, right?
Three had three pairs, two had two pairs.
At the beginning? Yeah. Oh, each one has its, each one has
the
number of pairs according to its successive number. Okay. So therefore for
three, you can only bring one pair because as soon as you
bring a second, you might be bringing that. Now similarly by four,
right, there are two fours that flew away. Okay. How many pairs
can you bring? So you can bring two, because even if you
brought two, you are definitely leaving over a pair of fours and
you're not fixing the identity. But any more, you might be hitting
into this and we're not worried that if you bring it, maybe
you're bringing one of the questionable ones, in which case then you're
hitting the questionable ones? No, the whole point is because each one
you're bringing it in the way that you don't fix the questionable
ones, you don't have to worry that you're bringing the questionable ones,
because
within each pair I'm ensuring that I'm not fixing all the questions
that are in the mix.
But maybe you, maybe the one that you're bringing is the question,
in which
case you're hitting the question. No, no, so what? If this is
a question, if this is really from number five, and this is
really from number two, I'm still safe because the way I'm bringing
five and two is ensuring that these aren't fixed. That's the whole
point, right?
I'm not bringing all the ones of two so that if accidentally
I'm going to bring a two over here, it's going to be
an undetermined two. And I'm not bringing all the ones of five,
which allows me to say that if I accidentally bring a five
here, it's going to be undetermined.
But maybe the one you brought is your עולה Olah. as a
two that is a...
That's exactly
why you don't know which one it is.
It could still be
you don't know any of them which it is, right? Who cares?
You don't have to know as long as some of the original
group is left. This identity will only be fixed if all of
the original group is brought, right? You got that? As long as
there's some twos unbrought, this has a flexible identity. And so that's
the whole reason why we're leaving stuff over, so that the things
that we do bring even if we wind up bringing from the
others have a flexible identity.
Okay, that's what I never got. I understand why it has a
flexible identity because I always thought like you know if one of
them is brought then the other one becomes the you know if
they're paired one is a חטאת Chatat.
and one is an עולה. Olah, No, I told you that yesterday.
You have to accept that you can have a group that is
larger than two group. That initially the whole size of the group
is defined not by multiple twos but by conceptually as a larger
group. You're right, if it was your way it would be much
stiffer. Okay, so that's the reason here that you are reducing two
from each group and only one from here is if you sort
of see this so that when you take away two you are
ensuring that you are because it lost in this example two fours
you're ensuring that there are fours left over so these identities are
not fixed. And that allows other קרבנות korbanot to be brought because
these are mixed up in the other things and you're bringing other
things. So the idea is to make sure you left over one
group so that the remaining things that have flown away do not
have a fixed identity. As I said presumably you could bring one
of them without the other but okay we're not going to get
into that. Now the problem is, so that explains the logic. The
problem that the מפרשים meforshim ask is that and I was waiting
for Michael to ask it but maybe everybody's still getting their head
around it
is there's a problem here which is because
by three right if you think about it by three okay two
flew here and three flew here and three flew over there. Okay
if I'm not bringing any for two I'm not bringing any of
them for two then that gives me more flexibility for three because
I don't have to be afraid that this one is going to
be brought. Is that clear? Meaning the reason by three right why
by three are we only bringing one group because as soon as
I brought this other group it would fix the identity, right? But
if I bring
but it's not even if it fixes the identity well I guess
it'll fix the identity of this it's also going to fix no
that's exactly the point. Let me bring this whole group okay now
the identity isn't fixed yet because there's still two out, right? So
this one will be brought. Fine, that one will be brought and
the identity will be fixed. Who cares? This is going into two.
We just said we're not bringing any from two. Is that clear?
Sort of? Yes? Meaning the reason I don't want to bring all
of these is because there are two out there and I don't
want both of them to be brought both of them to be
brought the wrong way. But this one might be brought it's going
this way but this is going that way and I'm saying I'm
not bringing any from two anymore. So why can't I go ahead
and bring all of the things from three? So anyway the מפרשים
meforshim ask this question the basic answer is you know לא פלוג
lo plug
we're just keeping it simple but I just wanted to point out
that you know the way the משנה mishna is working is it's
just operating on a rule. The principle of the משנה mishna. is
every time a bird flies in and flies out you lose one.
Okay and that's what the משנה Mishna sort of applied that principle
but this was explaining logic behind that principle. Okay, back to the
משנה. Mishna Are we having fun yet? Now okay now okay I
just פרח וחזר וחזר פוסל אחד בביאתו ואחד בחזירתו. parach vechazar vechazar
posel echad bevi'aso ve'echad bachazaraso. Now let's say of the ones that
were still I'm not going to do the logic but of the
ones that were still working like these were the ones you could
still bring. How many could you bring? Pairs could you bring of
all of this? One two three four six. Now of these that
were still good you have the whole same scenario. So of course
what are you going to be left with? You're going to subtract
two from each one: zero zero one two and this gets only
one subtracted because Because it's because it's the endpoint so it only
has the adjacent one. Okay, so that's just taking the same thing
and say what happens when it happened again. When you said it
happened again, does it happen... yes, it loses two. If one bird
goes in and one bird... In this case, not in this case,
I'm just saying as a principle. You said every time a bird
goes in you lose one, every time a bird goes out you
lose one. Okay, so you lose two in the examples where they
flew into it. Right, exactly. Well here it loses one bird and
one bird, it loses two in this trip and then it loses
two in that trip. So it loses a total of four birds,
but that's two sets. These are the number of sets. Okay? Yes,
clear? Or you want me to just draw it out for you?
Just multiply by four. No, no, no. I mean, I get that.
A bird comes in and a bird goes out, that's minus two
birds, right? Okay, then here a bird, on the way back into
number four, a bird goes in and a bird goes out, it's
minus two birds. Right. So its total is four birds or two
sets. Okay, thank you. Yeah. Okay, so it says, okay, פרח וחזר
פוסל אחד בהליכתו ואחד בחזירתו, Parach vechazar posel echad behalichato ve'echad bachazirato,
השלישית והרביעית אין להם כלום. Hashlishit veharevi'it ein lahem klum. So now
three and four are minus two, are minus one and two, go
down to zero. החמישית יש לה אחת, Hachamishit yesh la achat, השישית
יש לה שתיים, Hashishit yesh la shtayim, השביעית יש לה חמש. Hashvi'it
yesh la chamesh. Okay, zero, zero, one, two, five. Now, פרח וחזר
פוסל אחד בהליכתו ואחד בחזירתו, Parach vechazar posel echad behalichato ve'echad bachazirato,
and now we're going to do it again. So out of the
remaining one, we have the whole thing again of flying back and
forth, back and forth. So zero, zero, and then this is going
to be, we would think, four. Okay, like that. If we do
the whole thing again, another minus two. Okay. החמישית והשישית אין להם
כלום, Hachamishit vehashishit ein lahem klum, השביעית יש לה ארבע, Hashvi'it yesh
la arba, ויש אומרים השביעית לא הפסידה כלום. Ve'yesh omrim hashvi'it lo
hipsida klum. That the שביעית Shvi'it is lost nothing. Why did the
שביעית Shvi'it lose nothing? Because of the times it's flown back and
forth again? It doesn't matter. Because if you're not bringing any of
that stuff, right, what do you have to worry about here? I
mean, what exactly, you know, right? Now, the point is, is that
you can't exactly bring, I'm just trying to remind myself, can you
bring everything that's in the שביעית? Shvi'it? You can't, because wait, you
can't, because let's say you had some from group number one. No,
no, no, you can. Because the whole way that you did not
bring stuff there was ensuring that, wait, was ensuring that everything else
was undetermined. Right. Hold on, let me just think about this a
second. You've got two... Yeah. So anyway, some מפרשים Mefarshim actually say
that where it says השביעית לא הפסידה כלום, Hashvi'it lo hipsida klum,
it really means you can bring all of them. Because at this
stage, right, everything that you haven't brought was done to ensure that
the remaining birds were undetermined. So if the remaining birds are undetermined,
you might as well go ahead and bring everything. It's the same
reason we were saying by three you should have, right, more flexibility
here. Everything becomes a zero, so this should be maximized. But that's,
so what's the debate? The debate is again how much do you
sort of extend a type of a לא כלום? Lo klum? A
lot of people say that's correct, maybe here we should... Would these
people say the same thing by number three over there? No, so
that's it. You're right, that they wouldn't. But the question is when
you're left with only one group at that stage, maybe we should
say, look, let's face it, everything here is okay. Or at least
the question is how do you read לא הפסידה כלום? Lo hipsida
klum? לא הפסידה כלום, Lo hipsida klum, do you go back to
the original seven or לא הפסידה כלום Lo hipsida klum and at
least you stay at your, you know, at your five? You don't
have to go down to your four? Once these become zero, it
doesn't have to be affected by that because those became zero. But
that's really kicking in the logic as opposed to just applying the
rule. Okay. No, we don't distinguish. Like we just have a general
rule which we apply consistently even if it doesn't make sense. Okay.
ואם, Ve'im, we're almost done. This is it guys. ואם, Ve'im, after
this it's trivial. ואם, Ve'im, after this it's... ואם פרח מן המתות
וכולן הרי כולן ימותו. Ve'im parach min hametot vechulan harei chulan yamutu.
Now let's say from the birds that had to die flew amongst
any of these, then if a bird that had to die is
amongst them, the only reason we had flexibility was because it was
an undetermined status. But if there's a bird that had to die
was among them, then you don't know which one is that, you
have to let them all die. Now what is considered a bird
that had to die? So the מפרשים Mefarshim basically say is that
that would include a case of, remember we brought zero from one
and two, right? So the reason we brought zero was to let
the other ones have a more open status. So if we're bringing
zero, what are we going to do with these? we're going to
let them die. So therefore, if one of them flies into here,
that's פרח מן המתות, Parach min hametot, right? Which is why when
I gave you the next case I only said it was from
three and on. If one and two continued to fly, it would
be פרח מן המתות Parach min hametot and you'd have to let
them all die. Now I do want to point out that that
is a little bit of a חידוש. Chidush. to say that this
would be considered מתות. Metot. Right? Can you just? Can you just
explain to protect? Exactly. We might de facto not bring them and
let them die, but they don't have a הלכה Halacha that they
have to die. We could choose to bring these and not bring
the others, right? It's all a question of how are you going
to maximize the birds we're going to bring. So you could have
argued, you know, if these start afterwards flying into here, it's just
like all the groups got mixed up. We have a הלכה Halacha.
how do you deal with it when all the groups got mixed
up? You bring according to the smallest size group, that was yesterday,
right? So the fact that the מפרשים Meforshim assume that this is
considered מן המתות Min hametot is not explicit in the משנה Mishna.
and I'd have to say is an open question, 'cause that could
have just been a choice not to bring those, not that it
actually designates them as מתות. Metot. But that's the way you maximize
the other birds. But some of them, a lot of the מפרשים
Meforshim assume that that is מתות. Metot. Okay. That was the hard
משנה Mishna. for today. The rest is easy. Let's go. Then you
have to worry about tomorrow. We leave the hardest for last. Okay,
actually there are two more days left. Okay. כאן סתומה וכאן מפורשת.
Kan stumah vekan meforashet. Let's say you have an non-differentiated pair and
a differentiated pair. פרח מן הסתומה למפורשת, Parach min hastumah limeforashet, so
from the non-differentiated went into the differentiated. Now, יקח זוג לשני. Yikach
zug lasheni. You have to go ahead and and pair it up.
What does that mean? For the one that remains. What do you
do with the one that flew into? Okay, this is my חטאת,
Chatat this is my עולה, Olah. and I have something that flew
in. Now if I have something that flew in, if I know
what it is, it's relatively easy, just take it out. So presumably
it means I don't know what it is. If I don't know
what it means, it means I can't distinguish which any of them
are. Well if I can't distinguish which any of them are, this
is the least of the problem because the חטאת Chatat... and עולה
Olah. got mixed up. If חטאת chatas and עולה Olah got mixed
up, I can't bring it. Okay? So I can't bring anything here.
So if it flew into this group, that group got all mixed
up. That group can't be brought at all. What do I do
with my thing that's left? That's easy. That was the first משנה.
mishnah. Find a pair for the one that's left. I can't take
something from here because it obviously could be the wrong one. חזר
או חזר, Chazar o chazar, let's say it flew back from here
into here. Now that means it flew from a group that they
are all going to have to die, and that really is a
case of מתות. Metot. So I have no choice here, they're all
going to have to die and that flies back, so now it's
going to be a bird that's מתות, Metot, whichever one it is
flies in and gets mixed up with my good bird. או שפרח
מן המפורשות ראשון, O sheparach min hameforashot rishon, or forget the case
that they got mixed up. This was a חטאת, chatas this was
an עולה, Olah. and a pre-defined עולה Olah flew in, so it
got mixed up and now I can't tell which is which. Okay.
הרי כולן ימותו. Harei kullan yamutu. They all have to die. Now
really, if that, if this was a case where, if it was
a case where this I don't know which is which, so they're
all מתות Metot and it flies and gets mixed up, then then
that's obviously כולן ימותו Kullan yamutu with something that has to die
that gets mixed up. But if the עולה Olah... flew in and
got mixed up, they don't all have to die. And I know
it's an עולה. olah Then you know which one it is. That's
the thing. You started by knowing and now you don't know. But
if that were the case, that's what I'm saying, if you knew
this was the עולה olah, that flew out and then it got
mixed up and then you couldn't tell which is which, they don't
all have to die because then you just bring an עולה, olah,
right? That's the הלכה. Halacha? If an עולה olah. flies in then
you bring an עולה. olah So it has to be as Rivka's
saying, what it means is that at one time you separate, designated
these, but then you didn't know which was which and one of
them flew and got mixed up. So now you don't know. I
don't know if I've got a חטאת, chatas I don't know if
I've got an עולה, olah and then you're totally stuck and then
ימותו. Yamutu. All right. Now, next משנה. mishnah חטאת מכאן. Chatat mikan.
A lot of a lot of dying pigeons, Rivka. I know, I
know. חטאת מכאן ועולה מכאן וסתומה באמצע. Chatat mikan veolah mikan ustumah
be'emtza. You've got, this is your חטאת, chatas, right? This is your
חטאת. chatas This is your עולה. olah, I don't know how we're
going to remember that. And this is your pair in the middle,
your undifferentiated pair. This is defined as a clearly a חטאת chatas
and this is clearly an עולה. olah Okay. So now what's going
to happen? פרח מן האמצע לצדדים אחד הילך ואחד הילך. Parach min
ha'emtza latzdadim echad heilech ve'echad heilech. One bird flew to one side.
What's the הלכה? לא הפסיד כלום. Lo hifsid klum. You haven't lost
anything at all. This went, this this went to the חטאת chatat
side, this went to the עולה olah side. So now you give
all of these to the כהן. Kohen. Maybe this was ten חטאות,
Chataot, whatever it was, all of these to the כהן. Kohen. Since
these still are flexible identity, the כהן Kohen will just bring every
single one as a חטאת chatas. and when he gets to the
one which was from the undifferentiated, he won't know which is which,
but every single one he'll call a חטאת chatat and he'll make
that a חטאת. chatat Every single one he'll call an עולה. olah,
When he gets to that one he won't know it, but he'll
have called it an עולה olah and everything... שלום על ישראל. Shalom
al Yisrael. If you knew that the חטאת chatas, went over there
and the עולה... olah Yes, you knew that this was a pile
of חטאות Chataot and this was a pile of עולות, Olot, this
was undifferentiated and then they flew out. Although they... They were undifferentiated
they left but fine, so now differentiate them. Okay, not a problem.
לא הפסיד כלום. Lo hifsid klum. No, you haven't lost anything. אלא
יאמר, Ella yomar, you will say or the כהן Kohen says... Just
again to be exactly clear, the גמרא Gemara says what it was
and at the time of purchase, it's only the כהן, Kohen, not
so explicit in the משניות Mishnayot here. אלא יאמר, Ella yomar, you'll
say זה שהלך לכאן חטאת חטאת. Ze shehalach lechan chatat chatat. The
one that went to the חטאת... chatat Told you this was easier.
חזר לאמצע, chazar l'emtza, now from these birds here, these two groups
of birds, one bird of each flew back in. Now you've got
a problem, right? Because now you've got if you knew what your
original bird and you hadn't yet designated, then maybe you'd be okay.
But if you've already designated, you're stuck. Or anyway, how you don't
know it's your original bird, right? Maybe it's from a fixed עולה
olah and a fixed חטאת chatas, and they're in the middle and
they're mixed up, and if you don't know which is חטאת chatas
which is עולה, olah. you can't bring either. Okay, חזר לאמצע, chazar
l'emtza, הן ימותו, hen yamutu, any birds that are in the middle
that is a mixture of חטאת chatas and עולות, olas, you have
to let die. אלו elu and the ones on the side, יקרבו
לחטאת, yikarvu l'chatas, אלו יקרבו לעולה. elu yikarvu l'olah. This pile still
is a חטאת, chatas. this an עולה, olah but anything that gets
mixed up in the middle you can't use. חזר, chazar, now from
this pile that's a mix and they all have to die, they
went back to the side. Now everything has to die because one
of... something has to die. חזר או שפרח מן האמצע לצדדין. chazar
o sheparach min ha'emtza l'tzidadin. Now the או שחזר או שפרח o
shechazar o sheparach is funny, seems like it's the same case. Some
take out the word או. o. חזר ופרח מן האמצע לצדדין chazar
v'parach min ha'emtza l'tzidadin is how a lot of the מפרשים meforshim
read it. הרי כולם ימותו, harei kulam yamutu, then they all have
to die. Okay, easier things to remember. Something dies, gets mixed up,
they all have to die. Right. Right. Anyway, so okay, that was
that. Move it on. אין מביאים תורים כנגד בני יונה ולא בני
יונה כנגד תורים. ein mevi'in torin k'neged b'nei yonah v'lo b'nei yonah
k'neged torin. This is like totally unrelated to all of the other
discussion. We're no longer talking, I know, but we're no longer talking
about mixed up. The whole rest of the מסכת masechet is mixed
up. This is the one rule that's not about mixed up. It's
saying you have to bring two birds, a חטאת chatat and an
עולה. olah And the תורה Torah also says that you can bring
או מן התורים או מן בני היונה, o min ha-torin o min
b'nei ha-yonah, either from the pigeons or the turtle doves, whatever whatever
exactly meaning those are, I once had a whole blog post about
that. Now you cannot bring one of each species. You have to
bring the two have to come from the same species. Okay, so
אין מביאים תורים כנגד בני יונה, ein mevi'in torin k'neged b'nei yonah,
you don't bring a pigeon opposite a turtle dove, ולא בני יונה
כנגד תורים, v'lo b'nei yonah k'neged torin, or the reverse. כיצד, what's
this case? האישה שהביאה חטאת תור ועולתה בן יונה. ha'ishah shehevi'ah chatat
tor v'olasah ben yonah. Let's say her חטאת chatas. she brought as
a תור, tor, the pigeon, and her עולה olah she brought as
the turtle dove. So she brought different types. Which one is... she
has to do a do-over? So that's the pretty easy answer. Which
one would you say do a do-over for? You would say the
second. I would say, well there's a מחלוקת machlokes in the משנה.
mishnah I would say what the first opinion in the משנה mishnah
is: do the עולה olah over because because an עולה, olah the
first עולה olah maybe it didn't count for her חיוב, chiyuv, for
her obligation, but it could be a... it could be a free
עולת נדבה. olas nedavah. It's still a קדשי קרבן kodshei korban and
just do your obligatory עולה olah with a different one. But if
you do your חטאת chatas over, you've implicitly invalidated your first חטאת.
Okay, so you brought a חטאת and an עולה, olah they weren't
of the same type. One has to be a do-over. Which one
are we going to be a do-over for? So the first opinion
of the משנה says we're going to make the עולה olah, a
do-over. Says she brought her חטאת a תור tor and an עולה
olah בן יונה, ben yonah, תכפול ותביא עולת תור, tichpol v'tavi olas
tor, bring your עולה olah, again from the same thing of the
חטאת, of the pigeon עולה. olah Let's say she brought עולתה תור
וחטאתה בן יונה, olasah tor v'chatasah ben yonah, her עולה she brought
as a pigeon and her חטאת as a turtle dove. So which
one should she do as a do-over? תכפול ותביא עולה בן יונה,
tichpol v'tavi olah ben yonah, redo your עולה as a do-over, do
your עולה with a turtle dove. So again, I think even here
it's obvious because your obligation of an עולה you do as a
do-over but the one you already brought was still a קדשי קרבן.
kodshei korban. Okay, it wasn't your obligation because it didn't match the
חטאת, but it still could be כשר kasher as an independent קרבן.
korban. That's the first opinion. בן עזאי אומר, Ben Azzai omer, Ben
Azzai says what Michael said, הולכין אחר הראשון. holchin achar harishon. The
first one determines the set. So if your first one was an
עולה and that was a תור, tor, then your חטאת has to
be a תור. tor. And if your חטאת was a בן יונה,
ben yonah, was different from your עולה and your עולה was first,
presumably it was a פסול חטאת. pasul chatas. Okay, so according to
him, he would actually say I'm not... yeah, I'm going to go...
your first one determines the set, and even if that means that
you're going to have to have a פסול חטאת pasul chatas and
do a do-over for a חטאת. Now you're just applying the same
principles before essentially that, you know, what... that we've been having that
Ben Azzai always like conceptually just... I'm not saying one's way more
than the other one. Yeah, but there's an aspect here of fixing...
I see, that's an interesting point. You're saying it's similar to the
idea because you look at it as a group and the first
one was fixed. Okay, that's a nice point. Maybe that's why it's
more in this מסכת masechet or, you know, of the same theme.
האישה שהביאה חטאתה ומתה. ha'ishah shehevi'ah chatasah umetah. Now here again, this
is a משנה that's taught elsewhere, but it's repeated here. So now
we're just dealing with general הלכות halachos of birds which are not
about mixed up. A woman brought her חטאת and then she died.
So she has an עולה obligation. but she didn't bring it in
her life. יביאו יורשים עולתה. Yavi'u yorshim olatah. The יורשים yorshim are
allowed and actually have to bring the עולה, that's still an obligation
on the estate if this was a קרבן korban that the woman
was obligated in. And you can bring an עולה after somebody's dead;
it's not specifically had to be connected to the person. No, it's
her עולת חובה, olas chovah, but it doesn't require her to be
alive. If it were an עולת נדבה, olas nedavah, then what? Same
for her? No, but the point is that her obligation creates a
lien on the estate, means the estate is obligated to actually bring
it. If it were purely a נדבה, nedavah, then then they'd be
allowed to, but they wouldn't be obligated to. Here actually they have
to. Then they bring it, but then do they bring it as
an, you know, what are the, what are they bringing? Is the
כהן kohen saying this is for the נשמה neshamah of the dead
woman? No, I mean it's not, but that's the whole point, that's
since you can't, you don't say that, there's no כפרה למתים kaparah
lamesim and that's why you don't do it for a חטאת. But
this is, so you wouldn't say it's for the עליית נשמה aliyas
neshamah for her עליית נשמה, aliyas neshamah, but you would say that
this is being brought, you know, as part of the obligation that
was on her, that was on her, that was on her estate.
You know, so I, it doesn't, you're just saying about what כוונת
בעלים kavonat be'alim do you have? Yeah. עולה, who, I, that's a
good question. I assume, that's a good question. Who would be considered
the בעלים be'alim of the קרבן? korban? Would the יורשים, yorshim, well,
we say that the יורשים yorshim don't do, there's a מחלוקת machlokes
if יורשים yorshim do סמיכה, smichah, right? Does it say anything? No,
but that would really indicate, I know, but I'm just saying that
but to generalize your question, that would indicate, you know, to what
degree is a יורש yoresh considered to be the בעלים. be'alim. Presumably
it would depend on the, on the מחלוקת machlokes of whether the
יורש yoresh does סמיכה, smichah, whether the יורש yoresh is considered the
בעלים be'alim or not. Okay, now, עולתה ומתה, olatah umetah, she brought
her עולה and she died, לא יביאו יורשים חטאתה, lo yavi'u yorshim
chatatah, they would not bring it because a חטאת offering you can
only for people that are alive, not for people that are dead.
הדרן עלך קן סתומה. Hadran alach ken stumah. That was it for
today. Great. Wait till tomorrow to finish.